Olive Beaupré Miller Papers, 1864-1992
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Olive Beaupre Miller papers
1864-1992
1894-1958
Miller, Olive Beaupré
MS 104
13 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Publisher; Children's author; Teacher of English; and Christian Scientist. Founder of the publishing company, The Book House for Children, the first collection of children's literature graded to meet developing needs and abilities of children at different ages. Materials include published and unpublished writings, including creative short stories of her youth and extensively researched historical novels of her later years; correspondence; literary manuscripts; memorabilia; drawings; photographs; and autobiographies of maternal grandfather, Lorenzo Dow Brady, and husband, Harry Edward Miller.
Olive Kennon Beaupré was born in Aurora, Illinois on September 11, 1883 to William S. and Julia (Brady) Beaupré. She received her B.A. from Smith College in 1904 and returned to Aurora to work as an English teacher at East Aurora High School for two years. In spring of 1906 Olive met Harry Edward Miller, a salesman for D. Appleton and Company. Soon after meeting Olive, Harry went to work for Lamson Brothers, a Chicago-based grain brokerage firm. Olive and Harry were married October 2, 1907. Olive took her first trip to Europe in 1908, accompanied by her friend Alene Williams and a tour group, and later by Harry. After returning to the United States, Harry was transferred by Lamson Brothers, to Streator, Illinois, where he and Olive joined the Christian Science Church. In 1912 the Millers moved again when Harry was transferred to Chicago, Illinois. Their daughter, Virginia Beaupré Miller, was born December 30, 1912.
Olive began writing rhymes and stories to entertain her child, and was encouraged by Harry to publish some of her writings. In 1917, the same year the Millers moved to Winnetka, Illinois, P.F. Volland Company published "Sunny Rhymes for Happy Children." P.F. Volland Company published two more of Olive's works, "Come Play with Me" and "Whisk Away on a Sunbeam," in 1918. Olive also published selected stories and poetry in The Christian Science Monitor that year.
In 1919 Olive founded The Book House for Children publishing company with Harry, who had resigned from his job with Lamson Brothers. Olive assumed the title of Editor and published all of her subsequent material either solely through The Book House or through other publishing companies in conjunction with The Book House. On May 8 of the same year Olive had her second child John who died shortly after birth. Olive published the first volume of the My Book House series in 1920 and set to work on the next five volumes. My Book House became the first collection of children's literature which was graded to meet the developing needs and abilities of children at different ages.
The Millers returned to Europe with Virginia in 1923 to collect material in France and Holland for her next series of children's books. The first two volumes of My Travelship: "Nursery Friends from France" and "Little Pictures of Japan," were published in 1925, followed by "Tales Told in Holland" in 1926. In December of 1927 the Millers went to the Eastern Mediterranean where Olive collected material for more books, traveling through Egypt, Palestine, and Arabia.
Olive began publishing the nine volume series A Picturesque Tale of Progress in 1929. She spent the next year making trips to the Southwest U.S., Mexico, Guatemala, and Yucatan. In 1931 she returned to Europe to gather more material in Germany, Austria, and Yugoslavia. In 1933 Engines and Brass Bands was published by Doubleday Doran, and in 1934 Olive revised My Book House, expanding the series from six volumes to twelve.
Her involvement in introducing sex education to public schools at Winnetka, Illinois led Olive to write an article in the June 1934 edition of Childhood Interests, A Digest for Parents and Teachers entitled "How Mothers and Fathers May Tell Children the Facts of Sex," and in 1935 she collaborated with George L. Bird to edit the book How Life Begins.
When Olive and Harry were divorced in May 1935, he resigned his position as President of The Book House. In addition to being Editor, Olive was elected Vice-President by the Board of Directors, who hoped that this post would keep her from pursuing a more managerial role in the company. Olive achieved the position of Chairman of the Board in 1939 and held it until 1954. In 1939 Olive published Heroes, Outlaws and Funny Fellows with Doubleday Doran, and Heroes of the Bible a year later with Dickson Publishing Company.
The Book House for Children was sold to United Educators in 1954, and moved in 1955 to Tangley Oaks at Lake Bluff, Illinois. Olive remained Chairman of the Board in an advisory capacity until she retired in 1962. Then she moved to Tucson, Arizona where she lived with her daughter Virginia (Miller) Read and family until her death on March 25, 1968.
The Olive Beaupré Miller Papers consist of five linear feet (twelve document boxes) of notes and research materials, published and unpublished writings, business documents, correspondence, literary manuscripts and typescripts, memorabilia, drawings, and photographs, dating from 1864-1992. The bulk of the material dates from 1894-1958.
The Biographical series fills one box and includes clippings, articles, and unpublished biographical sketches of Olive and other Beaupré and Miller family members. There is also miscellaneous correspondence, Smith College Alumnae material, and photographs. Biographical and genealogical material of other family members appear after material about Olive. Olive transcribed stories that her aunt, Mary Marsh Beaupré, dictated about her uncle, Arthur Matthias Beaupré, who served as Consul-General to Guatemala and U.S. Minister to Colombia, the Netherlands, Luxemburg, and Cuba. There are also typescripts of autobiographies by her maternal grandfather, Lorenzo Dow Brady, and her husband, Harry Edward Miller.
Miller's writings and related papers make up aproximately one third of the collection. The Writings series consists of both unpublished and published works. The unpublished writings are arranged chronologically, and separated into two parts: the creative short stories and paper dolls of her youth and typescripts of extensively researched historical novels of her later years. Olive's writings and research materials provide a clear chronological progression of her development as a writer and researcher. Her writing displays a strong sense of personal style which can be traced from her childhood writings on. The Paper dolls and drawings are included with the childhood writings because they were an integral part of Olive's early story-making endeavors. She considered the drawings her way of creating stories before she learned the alphabet.
Also of interest in the Writings series is the correspondence between Edwin Read, Jr. and Margaret Pratt concerning sales tactics and the sales women for The Book House. The collection includes a signed, first edition copy of Engines and Brass Bands. Business documents and correspondence relating to published works are filed in the Writings series under each work.
The Notes and Research series is arranged by subject and encompasses approximately two-thirds of the collection (seven boxes). Olive's class notes, mostly of Smith College literature classes, fill one and a half boxes. There are three boxes of material from her last unpublished work, America, Johannes. Much of this is historical accounts of the first Dutch settlers in the United States. There are two boxes of research material for various writings which focus on the history of the Midwest, including maps and brochures from historic sites. In addition, there are notebooks which Olive kept of lists, plot summaries, and reviews of the books she read, dating from 1904 to 1962. Similar summaries are found among the research notes.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical
II. Writings
III. Notes and Research Materials
Books on Shelf
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Olive Beaupré Miller's papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in several installments from 1977 to 1994 by her daughter, Virginia Beaupré (Miller) Read. The first edition of Engines and Brass Bands was donated by Esther Booth Wiley, Class of 1934.
Search Terms
Children's literature, American--History--Sources; Children's literature--Authorship--Sources; Dutch--United States--History--Sources; Education, Elementary-United States--History--20th century--Sources; Middle West--History--Sources; Publishers and publishing--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Book House for Children (Chicago, Ill.)--History--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Brady, Lorenzo Dow, 1810-1892; Miller, Harry Edward, 1878-1952; Women in the professions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Beaupré family; Beaupré, Arthur, 1853-; Miller, Olive Beaupré; Miller, Olive Beaupré. My book house.
- SERIES I: BIOGRAPHICAL
  - Contents and notes on material located elsewhere (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Olive Beaupré Miller
    - Biographical sketches, clippings, family geneology, 1958-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
    - East Aurora High School, class of 1900 Golden Anniversary, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and other material, 1941-88 (Box 1)
    - Smith College: (Box 1)
      - Alumnae Association and 1904 Class Secretary: correspondence and printed material, 1931-63 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Speeches for Class of 1904 30th Reunion, 1934, and Smith College Club in Chicago, Illinois, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lorenzo Dow Brady, Arthur Matthia Beaupré, and William S. Beaupré: biographical sketches and typescripts, ca. 1864-1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arthur Matthias Beaupré: photographs, correspondence, typescript by Olive Beaupré Miller as dictated and edited by Mary Marsh Beaupré, 1902-41 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harry Edward Miller: biographical sketch, "Yesterdays of a small town boy" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs: Olive Beaupré Miller, 1900-43 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    [See also Flat File]
- SERIES II: WRITINGS
  - Unpublished work
    - Early writings and notebooks
      - Paper dolls and other drawings, 1887-96 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Notebooks of short stories with paper dolls (2 vol), ca. 1894-95 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Booklet of Poetry, ca. 1895 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - "A Story of the Bacon Rebellion" (manuscript), ca. 1895 (Box 2)
      - "Some Kind of Story" (manuscript), 1895 (Box 2)
      - "Claudius" (manuscript), undated (Box 2)
    - Novels
      - Dominion (typescript), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - The Wind Blows Free, formerly entitled The Land of Escape (typescript), undated (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
      - America, Johannes (typescript), undated (Box 3, Folder 15-19)
        - Correspondence, 1951-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Published work
    - The Searchlight: articles, Jan-Jun 1899 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Engines and Brass Bands
      - Correspondence, 1934-59 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Promotion, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Reviews, 1933-34 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Heroes of the Bible
      - Business documents, 1942-59 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence, 1940-63 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Promotion, 1923-31 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Reviews, 1940-42 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Heroes, Outlaws and Funny Fellows
      - Business documents, 1939-57 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Correspondence, 1938-59 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Promotion, 1939-48 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Research material, 1939-50 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Reviews, 1939-40 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Junior Instructor, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Poetry copyright material, 1946-57 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - "When Blue Sky Smiles": correspondence, 1945-63 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - My Book House
      - Alterations--new material, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Correspondence
        - From Elizabeth Chmiel about dispute over "The Little Engine That Could" rights, 1955-92 (Box 5, Folder 38)
        - Margaret Pratt (a.k.a. "Pratty") to Edwin Lewis Read, Jr., 1947-49 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Curriculum guides, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Promotion, 1946-70 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Reviews, 1920, 1951, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Packet of letters to Olive Beaupré Miller on 30th anniversary of My Book House, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Notebook of reviews, 1950-58 (Box 5, Folder 43a)
    - A Picturesque Tale of Progress: notebook of reviews, 1950-57 (Box 5, Folder 43b)
- SERIES III: NOTES AND RESEARCH MATERIALS
  - Smith College Materials
    - Class Notes, ca. 1900-04 (Box 6, Folder 44-51)
    - Class Notes, ca. 1900-04 (Box 7, Folder 52-54)
    - Finished Papers and notes for Literature Classes (manuscripts), 1904 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Lists and plot summaries
    - Plot summaries of books read, ca. 1904-06, undated (Box 7, Folder 56-58)
    - Books read listed by author (in address book), 1944-49 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Lists and plot summaries of books read, 1944-62 (Box 7, Folder 59a)
  - America, Johannes
    - Notes on Epic of America by James Truslow Adams (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - Geneology of Jans Anneke (Box 8, Folder 61-62)
    - De Lancey family (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Material on manors, Philipses, Schuylers, Van der Doncks (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Lamb family (Box 8, Folder 65-66)
    - Narrative of New Netherland, Stuyvesant (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Lamb family, New Netherland (Box 8, Folder 68-69)
    - "Used material" for America, Johannes (Box 9, Folder 70-73)
    - Notes for American, Johannes (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - "Used material" for chapters 23-24 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Source material on Guiana and Tobago incidents (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Guiana and South America (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Human body and medicine (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Kidd, Valentine (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Pilgrims, Riker (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Dirck Corssen Stam (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Ships, Weddings (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Used Notes for America, J.--Landy from Ryher (Box 10, Folder 83-84)
  - "Midwestern Material"
    - Miscellaneous book material (Box 11, Folder 85)
    - Central and Southern Illinois (Box 11, Folder 86)
    - Foreign settlements (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - Illinois (Box 11, Folder 88-89)
    - Maps (Box 12, Folder 90)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 12, Folder 91)
    - Mississippi Valley (Box 12, Folder 92)
    - Missouri (Box 12, Folder 93)
    - Natchez, New Orleans (Box 12, Folder 94)
    - Nationalities and races (Box 12, Folder 95)
    - New Harmony, Indiana (Box 12, Folder 96)
    - Ohio and Ohio River (Box 12, Folder 97)
    - St. Genevieve, Missouri (Box 13, Folder 98)
    - Notes on Society in America by Harriet Martineau (Box 13, Folder 99)
    - Timothy Dexter (Box 13, Folder 100)
    - Vincinnes, Indiana (Box 13, Folder 101)
    - Wisconsin (Box 13, Folder 102)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Olive Beaupré Miller and The Book House for Children, Dorothy Loring Taylor 1986
  - Engines and Brass Bands, Olive Beaupré Miller 1933
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - 3 oversize photographs of Olive Beaupré Miller, 1943 (Map-case Flat file)
  - 2 maps
    - Fox River Valley, Wisconsin, historic sites, undated (Map-case Flat file)
    - Northeastern states road map, undated (Map-case Flat file)
  - Mississippi Valley travel brochure, undated (Map-case Flat file)
  - Article re: Heber Jeddy Grant, Chicago Tribune, 1935 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Book jacket for Engines and Brass Bands, 1933 (Map-case Flat file)